SHEKHAR SINGH

Mechatronics Engineering Graduate

ssingh@optisolutions.co.za
LinkedIn: Shekhar Singh

♀ Cape Town, South Africa **↓** +27 81 040 1780

A UCT graduate in Mechatronics Engineering with a background in electromechanical design, and software engineering. Gained experience and training in Electrical and Mechanical engineering. In possession of strong leadership and communication skills due to numerous leadership positions occupied from a young age.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Microsoft AppFactory Intern OptiSolutions

Dec 2020 - Present

Cape Town, South Africa

 I joined the Microsoft AppFactory internship programme through OptiSolutions, where I've gained more software development experience. Achieved skills in Node, Git/Github, PowerApps, Azure, and app development.

Faculty Tutor

University of Cape Town (EBE Electrical department & EBE Mechanical Department

Feb 2017 - Dec 2020

♀ Cape Town, South Africa

- Tutored in mechanical and electrical design using various design programmes (including SolidWorks, AutoCAD, Altium Design, and KiCAD). I've also lectured some classes, and in doing so, I've gained teaching experience and further knowledge in each programme.
- Tutored in mechanical and electrical design using various design programmes (including SolidWorks, AutoCAD, Altium Design, and KiCAD). I've also lectured some classes, and in doing so, I've gained teaching experience and further knowledge in each programme.

Academic Researcher

University of Cape Town (EBE Electrical department)

♀ Cape Town, South Africa

• Worked as a student researcher for a professor in an academic project regarding ultrasonic applications for medical use.

Apprentice

ND Engineering

m Jun 2016 - Aug 2016

Ourban, KZN

 Worked as an apprentice with a group of other university students in which we trained in various departments in the this industrial company. I further developed my skills in fitting, turning and welding, as well as learned new skills in the manufacturing and assembly departments.

Apprentice

Intech Instrumentation

Mov 2015 - Jan 2016

Q Durban, KZN

- I worked under a team of mechanical and instrumental engineers, where I first learned trade skills involving fitting, turning, and welding.
- The company has specialized engineers of various fields, and with the workshop based in the Shell Chemicals PTY LTD plant site, I furthered my knowledge of electrical and instrumentation by working under the electrical team to maintain the electrical aspects of the plant.

SKILLS

	PROFESSIONAL:
	Leadership abilities Creativity
	Interpersonal skills Critical thinking
	Problem solving
	Customer service skills Teamwork ski
	Communication Adaptability
	Conflict Resolution Decision making
	Organization
_	
E	NGINEERING:
	Welding Fitting Turning
	PCB design Electronic design
	Mechanical design
	Controls System design
P	PROGRAMMING:
	C/C++ Embedded Systems Pythor
	HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript
	jQuery MATLAB Node/Express
	LaTeX SQL
	OFTWARE:
	Microsoft Office Suit
	MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps
	Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD
	Fusion360 Adobe Illustrator
	Adobe Photoshop Adobe Lightroom
	Adobe After Effects
	Adobe Media Encoder
	Autodesk Sketchbook STMCube
	Atollic Arduino arm MBED
_	
H	HOBBIES:
	Photography Photo editing

Videography

UX design

Graphics design

COMMUNITY & VOLUNTEER WORK

Community Outreach

(Various organizations)

2013 - Present

♀ Cape Town & Durban, South Africa

 Volunteered my services in many feeding schemes in different organizations over the years. These organizations include religious and academic societies, outreach programmes at the university, and small charity drives with my family over the festive period.

Animal Rescue

SPCA & LEAPs

Feb 2017 - Dec 2019

Cape Town, South Africa

 At the LEAPS Adoption Agency NGO and the Cape Town SPCA, I've volunteered my services in taking care of the dogs almost every and to promote the adoption of the dogs in the shelters.

EDUCATION

BSc Electrical Engineering (Specialising in Mechatronics)
University of Cape Town

₩ 2020

♀ Cape Town, South Africa

Matriculant Pass

Crossmoor Secondary School

2014

Ourban, KZN

Graduated with six (6) distinctions.

ACHIEVEMENTS & AWARDS

2019-2021:

Member of MENSA South Africa

2018:

• Chairperson of the UCT Hindu Student's Society

2017:

- Member of MENSA South Africa
- Sub-committee member of the UCT Hindu Student's Society

2016:

Class medal for Physics

2014:

- 3rd Academic position award (Crossmoor Secondary School)
- Deputy Head Prefect
- Student Council President
- Graduated from the MMI Mathematics and Physics programme

2013:

- Student council treasury
- CADSSA Table tennis (District team)

2012:

- · Representative on the student council
- · Graduated with black belt in Shotokan Karate
- Invited into the MMI Mathematics and Physics programme

LANGUAGES

English Afrikaans Hindi



REFEREES

Mr. Julian Kanjere Supervisor, AppFactory Team

- OptiSolutions
- **4** +27 76 333 5338

Mrs. Charmaine Findeis Lecturer, Dept. Mechanical Engineering

- University of Cape Town
- **** +27 21 650 2068

Mr. Justin Pead Lecturer, Dept. Electrical Engineering

- University of Cape Town
- **6** -